{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Surge tanks are used", "opta": "for storage water", "optb": "to increase the velocity in a pipeline", "optc": "as overflow valves", "optd": "to guard against water hammer.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As per IS : 1172-1963, water required per head per day for average domestic purposes, is", "opta": "50 litres", "optb": "65 litres", "optc": "85 litres", "optd": "105 litres", "opte": "135 litres.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In slow sland filters, the turbidity of raw water can be removed only up to", "opta": "60 mg/litre", "optb": "75 mg/litre", "optc": "100 gm/litre", "optd": "150 mg/litre.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Biochemical Oxygen Demand (B.O.D.) of safe drinking water must be", "opta": "nil", "optb": "5", "optc": "10", "optd": "15", "opte": "20", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acidity in water is caused due to", "opta": "Mineral acids", "optb": "Free CO2", "optc": "Iron sulphate", "optd": "Aluminium sulphate", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transitional middle portion of a logistic curve follows", "opta": "a geometric growth", "optb": "a logarithmic growth", "optc": "a first over curve", "optd": "a constant rate.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Excess quantities of iron and manganese in water, cause discolouration of clothes", "optb": "Lead and barium salts have toxic effect", "optc": "Arsenic and selenium are poisonous to human health", "optd": "Higher copper content affects the lungs", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following regarding fire hydrants", "opta": "Fire hydrants are fitted in water mains at 100 m to 150 m apart at fire", "optb": "The minimum water pressure hydrants, is kept 1.5 kg/cm2", "optc": "The water at pressure 1 to 1.5 kg/cm2 is made available for 4 to 5 hours for constant use", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific retention is least in case of", "opta": "Clay", "optb": "Sand", "optc": "Silt", "optd": "Coarse gravel.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "B.O.D. of treated water should be", "opta": "10 ppm", "optb": "25 ppm", "optc": "20 ppm", "optd": "30 ppm", "opte": "Nil.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used pump for lifting water in water supply mains, is", "opta": "axialflow pump", "optb": "reciprocating pump", "optc": "rotary type pump", "optd": "centrifugal pumps", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Economic height of a dam is the height corresponding to which", "opta": "cost of the dam per unit of storage is minimum", "optb": "amount of silting is less", "optc": "cost of dam per unit storage is maximum", "optd": "free board provided is least", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Distribution mains of any water supply, is normally designed for its average daily requirement", "opta": "100%", "optb": "150%", "optc": "200%", "optd": "225%.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of water is", "opta": "7 water it is said to be neutral", "optb": "less than 7 it is said to be acidic", "optc": "more than 7 it is said to be alkaline", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In pressure supply mains, water hammer pressure is reduced by providing", "opta": "sluice valves", "optb": "air valves", "optc": "pressure relief valves", "optd": "none of the these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P0, P1, P2 be the populations of a city at times t0, t1 and t2 = 2t1, the saturation value of the population Ps of the city, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water supply system includes", "opta": "digging a well for water", "optb": "construction of dams", "optc": "construction of canals", "optd": "entire arrangement from source to distribution.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of a pipe", "opta": "reduces its life span", "optb": "reduces its carrying capacity", "optc": "adds colour to water", "optd": "adds odour to water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most satisfactory formula for an estimate of fire demand Q for a city of population P in thousands for Indian conditions, is", "opta": "", "optb": "Q = 1640 P (1 - 0.01 P)", "optc": "Q = 3180 P", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Detention period for plain sedimentation tanks ranges between 4 to 8 hours", "optb": "Detention period for sedimentation tanks, using coagulants usually ranges between 2 to 4 hours", "optc": "The horizontally flow velocity in sedimentation tanks, is generally limited to 0.3 m/minute", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Kuichling's formula, fire demand in litres per minute for a population of P thousands, is", "opta": "3182 P", "optb": "", "optc": "4637 P [1 - 0.01 P]", "optd": "5663 P.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum permissible nitrites in public water supplies, is", "opta": "Nil", "optb": "0.5 P.P.M.", "optc": "1.0. P.P.M.", "optd": "1.5 P.P.M.", "opte": "200 P.P.M.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A high velocity of wash water is required for", "opta": "rapid gravity filter with strainers", "optb": "rapid gravity filter without strainers", "optc": "slow sand filter with strainers", "optd": "slow sand filter without strainers", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distribution pipes, drain valves are provided at", "opta": "lower point", "optb": "higher point", "optc": "junction points", "optd": "any where.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of well pipes may not be reduced by", "opta": "reducing the draw down and the pumping rate", "optb": "reducing the flow velocity", "optc": "using thicker pipes", "optd": "using screens having larger area of openings", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Manholes along the mains from the source to a city are provided at 500 m intervals in", "opta": "steel pipes", "optb": "R.C.C. pipes", "optc": "hume steel pipes", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The population growth curve is", "opta": "S-shaped curve", "optb": "parabolic curve", "optc": "circular curve", "optd": "straight line", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Turbidity of raw water is a measure of", "opta": "suspended solids", "optb": "acidity of water", "optc": "B.O.D.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If V is total consumption of water in litres for a population of N individuals, per capita consumption or water allowance for the water supply Q, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water supply includes", "opta": "collection, transportation and treatment of water", "optb": "distribution of water to consumers", "optc": "provision of hydrants for fire fighting", "optd": "mains, sub-mains and branch lines of water supply", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Asbestos pipes are", "opta": "light in weight and easy to transport", "optb": "highly resistant to corrosion", "optc": "high flexible to accommodate deflection upto 12\u00b0", "optd": "very much smooth and hydraulically efficient", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum depth of sedimentation tanks is limited to", "opta": "2 m", "optb": "3 m", "optc": "4 m", "optd": "5 m", "opte": "6 m.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By boiling water, hardness can be removed if it is due to", "opta": "calcium sulphate", "optb": "magnesium sulphate", "optc": "calcium nitrate", "optd": "calcium bicarbonate", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Q is the discharge from an unconfined tube well with depression head s through its pipe of radius rw. If the radius of influence is R, the length of the required strainer, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determining the velocity of flow of underground water, the most commonly used non-empirical formula is", "opta": "Darcy's formula", "optb": "Slichter's formula", "optc": "Hazen's formula", "optd": "Lacy's formula.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The least thickness of class B cast iron (spun) pipe, is", "opta": "7.2 mm", "optb": "7.9 mm", "optc": "8.6 mm", "optd": "10 mm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to IS : 1172-1963, a minimum of 135 litres of water capita per day, is required for", "opta": "Boarding schools", "optb": "Nurses home and medical quarters", "optc": "hostels", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The R.L. of ground water table on the sides of a valley is 1505 m whereas R.L. of the stream water is 1475 m. If 60\u00b0 slope consists of pervious soil between R.L. 1485 m to 1500 m, the gravity spring may be expected at the point of reduced level", "opta": "1500 m", "optb": "1505 m", "optc": "1475 m", "optd": "1485 m.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The factor affecting per capita demand, is", "opta": "size of the city", "optb": "climatic conditions", "optc": "pressure in water mains", "optd": "cost of water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following. The underground sources of water, is from", "opta": "wells", "optb": "springs", "optc": "infiltration wells", "optd": "storage reservoirs", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Disinfection of drinking water, is done to remove", "opta": "odour", "optb": "bacterias", "optc": "turbidity", "optd": "colour.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sunlight", "opta": "helps growth of bacterias", "optb": "impedes growth of algae", "optc": "increases dissolved oxygen content", "optd": "reduces turbidity.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expected discharge to be obtained from an open well sunk in coarse sand is 0.0059 cumec. If the working depression head of the well is 3 m, the minimum diameter of the well, is", "opta": "2 m", "optb": "2.25 m", "optc": "2.50 m", "optd": "2.75 m", "opte": "3.00 m.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Average annual rainfall at any station is the average of annual rainfall over a period of", "opta": "7 years", "optb": "14 years", "optc": "21 years", "optd": "28 years", "opte": "35 years.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Time of concentration", "opta": "is the time taken, for precipitation", "optb": "duration of rainfall.", "optc": "time taken for all the ran off to reach the drain", "optd": "time taken for the storm water to travel from the most remote point to the drain.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If four fires break out in a city of population 40 lakhs and if each hydrant has three streams and duration of each fire is four hours, the total quantity of water required, is", "opta": "1880 kilo litres", "optb": "2880 kilo litres", "optc": "3880 kilo litres", "optd": "4880 kilo litres.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fire demand of a city may be worked out by", "opta": "Kuichling's formula", "optb": "Freeman formula", "optc": "Under Writers formula", "optd": "Bustan's formula", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aeration of water is done to remove", "opta": "odour", "optb": "colour", "optc": "bacterias", "optd": "hardness", "opte": "turbidity.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The yield of a rapid gravity filter as compared to that of slow sand filter, is", "opta": "10 times", "optb": "15 times", "optc": "20 times", "optd": "30 times", "opte": "35 times.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}